<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A watch-word, or, The allarme, or, A good take heed A sermon preached at White-Hall in the open preaching place the last Lent before King Charles. By the R.R. Father in God T.F. the then bishop of Landaffe, now of S. Dauids.</title>
            <author>Field, Theophilus, 1574-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118351</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853558</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853558</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00733)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A watch-word, or, The allarme, or, A good take heed A sermon preached at White-Hall in the open preaching place the last Lent before King Charles. By the R.R. Father in God T.F. the then bishop of Landaffe, now of S. Dauids.</title>
                  <author>Field, Theophilus, 1574-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper for Nath. Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text ends on D7v; Folger Library copy lacks D8; Bodleian Library copy has on D8r the last page of an (extra? presentation?) epistle by Field, probably to the Duke of Buckingham--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A watch-word to waken vs.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Watch-Word, <hi>OR,</hi> The Allarme, <hi>OR,</hi> A good Take Heed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A SERMON Preached at</hi> White-Hall <hi>in the</hi> open Preaching place the laſt Lent <hi>before King CHARLES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the R. R. Father in God T. F. the then Biſhop of <hi>Landaffe,</hi> now of S. Dauids.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Tho. Harper <hi>for</hi> Nath. Field.</p>
            <p>1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS SACRED MAIESTIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>READ <hi>SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAIGNE,</hi> Though it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> to tranſlate me into the
<pb facs="tcp:18945:3"/> number of thoſe <hi>Magi,</hi> who giue gold for <hi>New-yeares gifts</hi> (for which the great Biſhop of our ſoules bleſſe you) yet J cannot ſuddenly leaue my Cuſtome for theſe many yeares payed to your bleſſed Father and Selfe, of preſenting Paper withall to wrap it in. This more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than gold, For, for want of <hi>(Good take heed)</hi> Men run the hazard, and fall into danger of Body,
<pb facs="tcp:18945:3"/> Soule, and Eſtate. The times are dangerous, our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies many and cruell, no man free. Here's a <hi>Good take heed</hi> for all, It is vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the loweſt of your Subiects, as for your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Selfe:</hi> but moſt needfull for <hi>You,</hi> ſince your Sacred <hi>MAIESTIE is worth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 3. <hi>Lament.</hi> 4. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ten thouſand of vs,</hi> yea, you are the <hi>breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils,</hi> and on your ſafety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends all ours. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ouchſafe
<pb facs="tcp:18945:4"/> to turne a gracious Eye, as you lent a patient Eare, to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your MAIESTIES faithfull ſeruant <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18945:4"/>
            <head>A VVATCH-WORD TO WAKEN VS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>DEVT. 4. 9.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Attende tibi;</hi> Take heed to thy ſelfe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Counſell, ſhort and pithy. Theſe words, like REVBEN; are ſtrong, full of life, though few in number, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 33. 6. Here is (as <hi>S. Baſil</hi> ſpeakes) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the full weight of few words. <hi>Virtus</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18945:5"/> 
               <hi>maxima, in mole minimâ,</hi> very, very much in a little, <hi>Ilias in Nuce, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> Iliads in a Nut-ſhell, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> In ſearching the veines of the earth (ſaith <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus)</hi> we finde a little gold in a great deale of Ore: But in ſearching the Mynes of holy Scriptures, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of a little ground, we finde a great deale of gold.</p>
            <p>They are the words of a great Commander, <hi>Moyſes</hi> the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Though (as hee excuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) he was <hi>ſlow of ſpeech,</hi> yet was he <note place="margin">Exod. 4. 10.</note> deepe in knowledge, well ſeene in <hi>all the learning of the Aegyptians,</hi> and <note place="margin">Acts 7. 22.</note> better learning then theirs. He was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, weighty in his ſentences. And here is <hi>Imperatoria breuitas,</hi> a Lord-like breuity, the more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the word he giues, carries with it. He ſpeakes <hi>ex Cathedrâ,</hi> his word is a law. 'Tis ſhort, for feare mans
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18945:5"/> brittle memory ſhould come ſhort of it; and to avoide obſcurity, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and re-inforced in the words following, <hi>Et cuſtodi, &amp;c.</hi> And keepe thy ſoule diligently, leſt being ſhort and darke, it might be ſlippery too, and ſlip the ſooner out of minde and memory. <hi>Duo verba, duo lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaria.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 16.</note> Theſe two words, like the two great lights in heauen, ſerue to direct vs all in all our wayes. As ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall lights they looke vpon all that looke vpon them, and caſt their beames vpon euery head that heareth mee this day. They compaſſe this great aſſembly (euen euery one) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their <hi>ſpheare,</hi> yea, all the men of the world. There is no ſonne of man that's out of the compaſſe of this Text. Now God giue Grace, that euery heart here preſent, may hence borrow ſome influence, light, and motion. Haue ye not ſeene the great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18945:6"/> 
               <hi>lights</hi> of Heauen mounting aboue the <hi>Horizon,</hi> how they firſt ſhine vpon the <hi>Hills,</hi> and high <hi>Cedars;</hi> and after vpon the <hi>vallies,</hi> and lower <hi>ſhrubs?</hi> Euen ſo <hi>This,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>lights,</hi> or <hi>Caueats, Imprimis, Primos,</hi> doe moſt eminently direct men in <hi>eminency,</hi> and (not skipping ouer <hi>medios,</hi> thoſe of the middle ſort) in due order deſcend <hi>ad infimos,</hi> to them of the lower forme, call vpon all Gods people (as it were) by the <hi>poll,</hi> euen <hi>from Him that ſitteth vpon the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 11. 5</note> 
               <hi>Throne, to him that grindeth at the Mill.</hi> See this graduall deſcent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 3. <hi>The mountaines ſhall bring forth peace, and the little hils righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe vnto the people.</hi> Gods Grace is like the <hi>deaw of Hermon;</hi> like the <hi>pretious oyntment which was powred</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 133. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vpon Aarons head, deſcended on his beard, and to the vtmoſt skirts of his garments.</hi> Behold heere is a <hi>Beacon</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18945:6"/> ſet on fire on the holy Mount. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houes euery one of vs to looke to himſelfe. Some great ſudden danger there's towards from within, and from without too. <hi>Homo homini Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> A man is a perilous beaſt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſhould be <hi>cuſtos,</hi> a keeper; who ſhould be <hi>Deus,</hi> a God. <hi>Cain</hi> loſt himſelfe, when hee refuſed to be <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 9.</note> his <hi>Brothers keeper,</hi> which euery man ſhould be, much more his owne. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Scneca.</note> 
               <hi>alteri Theatrum ſumus,</hi> we are all Theaters one to another; wherein wee may obſerue what's <hi>well</hi> acted, what's <hi>amiſſe.</hi> Yea euery man is a <hi>Citie,</hi> a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> a <hi>World</hi> within himſelfe. Ye are not preſt to any forraigne ſeruice: Euery man is both <hi>Cuſtos,</hi> and <hi>Caſtrum,</hi> the <hi>Watch,</hi> and the <hi>Cittadell;</hi> when the <hi>Beacon</hi> is fired, when this Alarme <hi>(Attende ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi)</hi> ſounds in our eares, he that doth not gird vp his loynes, hee that doth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18945:7"/> not ſtand vpon his guard, is a traytor to his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>I come not into this Preſence with an <hi>Attende mihi,</hi> a ſuit for my ſelfe, nor <hi>Attende gregi, Take heed to thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 20. 28</note> 
               <hi>flocke;</hi> But like the poore <hi>Italian</hi> Beggar with an <hi>Attende tibi: For Gods ſake be mercifull, be charitable to thine owne ſoule.</hi> If euer precept came home to the heart, it is this; if euer a charge was reaſonable, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, it is this, <hi>Attende tibi;</hi> be thine owne <hi>Guard,</hi> and <hi>Guardian, Ouerſeer,</hi> and <hi>Keeper.</hi> I may tearme it a Writ of <hi>Ne exeat,</hi> to confine euery rouing eye, and euery ſtragling ranging thought. Looke not, thinke not on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things without you, nor on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, on the outward appearance of things, the iugling ſhewes of the world: <hi>Non alijs, non alienis, non tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is; ſed Attende tibi;</hi> looke not at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons, other matters, thinke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18945:7"/> not on thine owne buſineſſe. Let not thy ſoule gad abroad with <hi>Dinab,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 1. Pſal. 4. 4.</note> but <hi>commune with thine owne heart,</hi> retire to thy beſt <hi>Fort,</hi> and arme thy ſelfe againſt the ſubtile ſtratagems of <hi>Sathan.</hi> Here is <hi>periculum animae,</hi> thy ſoule lyes at the ſtake, thy ſoule lyes a bleeding, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> are powerfull perſwaders. <hi>Theſe be the perilous Times</hi> in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtickes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. This world is the wilderneſſe of <hi>Sinne, Exod.</hi> 16. 1. the very <hi>Region of Death.</hi> Vnder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtone there is a Scorpion, and in euery buſh a fiery Serpent. <hi>In auro,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Hierom. S. Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>in cibo laquei.</hi> There are ſnares in our Coffers, and ſnares in our diſhes, there is death in the pot, <hi>Mors in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 4. 40</note> 
               <hi>ollâ, mors in ollis carnium, etiam in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu noſtro Synones.</hi> Our boſome is a <hi>Troian Horſe,</hi> and within it are the worſt traitors, the moſt dangerous enemies. 'Tis time to looke to our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18945:8"/> 
               <hi>ſelues.</hi> So that whether I looke on the <hi>place</hi> we ſtand in which is <hi>holy ground;</hi> or the <hi>time</hi> we are met in, which is the <hi>holy time of Lent;</hi> or the face of <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> which is <hi>mangled</hi> with ſelfe-giuen wounds, and <hi>beſmeared</hi> with her owne bloud; or the <hi>perſons</hi> before whom, and to whom we ſpeake; or the importance of the <hi>meſſage;</hi> ſo neerely concerning euery ſoule here preſent: in all theſe conſiderations, <hi>Moſes</hi> is a neceſſary Monitor and Remembrancer at euery mans elbow, and eare, with an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende tibi,</hi> a <hi>Take heed to thy ſelfe:</hi> yea, <hi>Behold a greater then Moſes is here,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>He,</hi> by whom the Goſpell came, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, the great ſhepheard of all our ſoules. Solus verus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only deliuerer of his people, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a Type. The ſpirit of <note place="margin">Deut. 18. 15.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> in the mouth of <hi>Moſes</hi> doth ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle our dull, and drowſie ſences with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18945:8"/> an <hi>Attende tibi.</hi> This my Text is to paſſe as a <hi>Watchword</hi> from one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; to which military forme of communicating the Watch-word, the warlike Prophet alludes where hee ſaith, <hi>Thy word runneth very</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 147. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſwiftly,</hi> when the Watch-word is once giuen by the Generall, 'tis ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly in euery quarter of the Armie. Entertaine then this <hi>Text</hi> as a <hi>Watch-word</hi> from the <hi>Lord of hoaſts,</hi> ecchoed in the eares of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by their great <hi>Leader Moſes, Take heed to thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our orderly proceeding, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>diſperſing</hi> than <hi>diuiding</hi> this Text, not long enough for a diuiſion, (for a Watch-word muſt be carried entire:) let your attention go along with me, &amp; by the guidance of Gods holy Spirit I ſhall ſhew you three <hi>watches</hi> and <hi>wards</hi> implyed in <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende tibi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>Attende corpori,</hi> a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18945:9"/> ſtrict guard ouer the body, in appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euery man to be the <hi>Squire of his owne body.</hi> For as there is a body of ſinne, ſo there are ſinnes of the body; corporall vncleanneſſe, and fleſhly <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1</note> luſts, which are the Diuels Souldiers, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 7.</note> to fight againſt the ſoule. There is a fault in the <hi>Caske,</hi> a ruſt of the <hi>Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd,</hi> the body is but <hi>Vagina,</hi> the <hi>Sheath,</hi> the faculties of the ſoule are the <hi>weapons:</hi> Scowre both for the <hi>watch</hi> and the <hi>warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, <hi>Attende animae,</hi> the <hi>ſoules ward,</hi> and this muſt be more carefully kept: For by the ſinnes of the body (luſt and drunkenneſſe) men become <hi>beaſts;</hi> but by the ſinnes of the ſoule <hi>(Pride, Enuie,</hi> and ſuch like) men become Deuils.</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>Attende Deo,</hi> the <hi>watch</hi> on our bulwarke, moſt careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be kept, <hi>Our waiting vpon God:</hi> which is requited with Gods watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18945:9"/> ouer vs. This alone ſecures body and ſoule. In vaine doe we truſt our blinde skouts, and drowzy Centinels, <hi>except the Lord keepe</hi> our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our Citie and our Cinque ports. Our firſt Watch may be called <hi>Cuſtodia Carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Cuſtodia Palatij,</hi> the third <hi>Cuſtodia Templi.</hi> The Watch is ſet, and the watch word giuen. Three Watches there were, before we come to reuew them in order, liſten we a while to the two voices that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vs to diligence in keeping this watch. The firſt is <hi>Vox Naturae,</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature would preſerue it ſelfe, and by naturall inſtinct preacheth, (as it were) this Text to man, to euery man, <hi>Attende tibi, Take heed to thy ſelfe.</hi> The <hi>Roe</hi> auoides the toiles, by the quickneſſe of her ſight (as <hi>S. Baſil</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </note> ſaith) being therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Fruſtra iacitur rete ante ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los pennatorum,</hi> ſurely in vaine the <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 17.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18945:10"/> Net is ſpred before the eyes of any Bird. The Birds haue eyes to ſee, and wings to eſcape the Springes. And ſhall onely man, like a tame foole, run his necke into euery nooſe? In vaine then hath God giuen him reaſon, which flies beyond the ſwiftneſſe of of any wing, which ſees beyond the compaſſe of any eye; by reflection, ſees into it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>vox Gratiae, the voyce of Grace,</hi> and that riſeth many notes higher. <hi>Take heede to thy ſelfe, take heede of thy ſelfe.</hi> For man is turned rebell to God, thereby become a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Aſaſſinate to himſelfe. <hi>Nemo laeditur niſi a ſeipſo, no man takes hurt but by his owne fault.</hi> Take heede of this, looke to thy being: looke to thy eternall being; looke to thy ſoule, the life of thy body; and looke vp to <hi>God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the life of thy ſoule. <hi>Ipſe eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> animae tuae, for God is thy life</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 20</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18945:10"/> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 20. And here by the way let me poynt at the <hi>goodneſſe of God, and our owne benefit:</hi> both are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in this watch-word, <hi>Attende, take heede, On Gods part,</hi> ther's <hi>Gratia excitans, A Grace ſtirring vs vp:</hi> our benefit, (if we giue due attendance) is <hi>Salus</hi> ſafety, of <hi>ſtate, body</hi> and <hi>ſoule.</hi> By nature we are careles, and drowzy in matters of ſaluation; like the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> wee lie <hi>open</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 18. 7. 1 Sam. 26. 7</note> yea like <hi>Saul</hi> wee are in a dead ſleepe, we may looſe our armes, our liues, our ſoules before we awake. It is a remarkeable art of <hi>Gods</hi> exciting Grace, to <hi>goade</hi> vs in this <hi>lethargie,</hi> to quicken euery man with an <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de tibi, take heede to thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>exciting</hi> Grace doth ſnatch vs out of the fire and water. It called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Lot,</hi> to auoyde that hell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <note place="margin">Ge. 19. 15.</note> fire and brimſtone. It ſtirred vp <hi>Noah</hi> to prepare an <hi>Arke</hi> againſt the <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 18.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18945:11"/> deluge: and it ſtill ſweetely whiſpers in euery one of our eares; <hi>Looke to thy ſelfe:</hi> prepare an <hi>Arke,</hi> now that God doth threaten an <hi>inundation</hi> of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Euery <hi>paſſenger</hi> in a ſhip is to looke to himſelfe, the <hi>Pilote</hi> more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to all. <hi>Quis vtilem cauſae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Ambroſe.</note> 
               <hi>iudicet, quem videt invtilem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſuae? Who will eſteeme that man vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for another man, that is not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for himſelfe?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> The <hi>Lion</hi> King of beaſts, and the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> King of birdes are moſt vigilant and circumſpect. Our <hi>Moſes</hi> in the text ſtout as a <hi>Lion,</hi> but meeke as a <hi>Lambe;</hi> ſtrong-tallond as an <hi>Eagle,</hi> but innocent as a <hi>Doue;</hi> is a paterne of a <hi>pious</hi> and a <hi>prudent</hi> Gouernour; who lookes to the ſafety of Iſrael in ſtate, body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>And when <hi>Moſes</hi> doth call vpon vs, to <hi>looke to our ſelues,</hi> wee ſhould bee ready to looke to <hi>Moſes.</hi> How for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18945:11"/> ought all true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to be to powre in their oyle for ſupply, rather then the light of Iſrael ſhould bee put out? And ſo now I come to the three watches: and firſt of <hi>Cuſtodia carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> or <hi>corporis,</hi> the watch ouer our bodyes.</p>
            <p>Wee are here in the body as in <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cuſtodia corporis.</hi>
               </note> a priſon, or darke dungeon: Some <hi>lights</hi> or <hi>inlets</hi> we haue, but they ſerue onely to let in ſinne. They more abaſe the body who will haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy no better than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Sepulchre, (which is trew of the ſurfetted body) wherein the ſoule lies buried. Wee will allow it to be an <hi>inſtrument</hi> of the ſoule, but a dull and vntoward one: <hi>Corpus degrauat animam, the body is a burthen to the ſoule,</hi> ſaith the <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 9. 15.</note> Bee it one of the eſſentiall parts of man; 'tis the worſer, the <hi>earthy,</hi> and the <hi>brute</hi> part. And here admire we with adoration, and adore we with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18945:12"/> admiration, the wiſdome and power of <hi>God,</hi> who vnited and ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſo ſweete and ſtable a yoke of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage (as it were) two ſo vnſuitable things, as are <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>Fleſh;</hi> which fleſh of ours, (through the taint of ſinne) like <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, becomes a boſome <hi>enemie,</hi> a trayterous <hi>inmate</hi> to our ſelues, a <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> and <hi>pander</hi> for Sathan. I take it now as it is, a <hi>cage of vncleane birds,</hi> a foule <hi>denne</hi> of beaſtly <hi>luſts:</hi> for being ſwept, it is a <hi>temple of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 19</note> If we giue the body too much, <hi>wee feede a foe,</hi> If too litle, we <hi>kill a friend.</hi> It behooues vs therefore in a godly iealouſie, to beate downe this <hi>rebell</hi> fleſh; who like <hi>Platoes</hi> friend is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a changeable creature,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Camelion:</hi> Sometimes ſo treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> cry out <hi>Crucifigatur, crucifigatur,</hi> let him be crucified. Sometime ſo obedient,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18945:12"/> that Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> reſtores her to her dowry, and the right of a wife, <hi>Amet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Adam Euam ſuam, Amet Anima car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſuam, ita tamen amet, vt non to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in carnem tranſeat.</hi> Let Adam loue his Eue, the ſoule her fleſh; but let her ſo loue it, that ſhe takes heede that ſhee become not altogether fleſhly. While ſhee is as <hi>Sarah</hi> was to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>cals the ſoule Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 6. ſhe is worthy to be loued and cheriſhed. Yet take we heede, that by fauouring of the body too much, we effeminate not the ſoule. Now if I ſhould make an anatomie of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I could diſcouer in euery limme, in euery veyne and artery, an Inlet for <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Sathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body is as <hi>tinder,</hi> apt to be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by euery ſpark the Deuil caſts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. It is therefore requiſite, that this powder be kept in cloſe veſſels, and that the paſſages be ſtopt; according
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18945:13"/> to the rule of Saint <hi>Gregorie: Ad cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Gregory</note> 
               <hi>munditiem ſenſuum diſciplina ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanda eſt.</hi> Clenſe the Limbecke of the ſenſes, leſt thence ſome pollution drop into the ſoule. The <hi>Arabians</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is elegant: <hi>Obſtrue quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtras, vt luceat domus,</hi> ſhut the fiue windowes, that the houſe may be lightſome. <hi>Attende oculis, Take heed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Eyes.</note> 
               <hi>to thine eyes,</hi> that they looke not out to behold vanitie, that they grow not red through luſt and drunkenneſſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Et dixit quidam, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in oculis,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Pet. 2. 14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Greeke ſignifies <hi>Girles,</hi> and the pupils of the eyes. S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw both together, <hi>Eyes full of adultery.</hi> The Eye is an <hi>Arch-traitour</hi> to the heart, with whom it is of <hi>counſell;</hi> yet keepes <hi>intelligence</hi> with the Deuill, mans grand enemie: <hi>blabs</hi> to Him, his moſt ſecret and ſudden thoughts; thereby <hi>excites</hi> him to aſſault vs, when we are at weakeſt; and vpon his firſt aſſault, <hi>yeelds</hi> vp our ſtrongeſt Fort.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18945:13"/> Vntill <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> luſted with their eyes, <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Sathan</hi> entred <note place="margin">Gen 3. 1.</note> not their hearts. An ill thought is brought forth, growne vp, and able to worke, before one can ſay, <hi>Take heed, he that looketh vpon a woman &amp; luſteth after her,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that caſt of his <note place="margin">Math 5. 28</note> eye, <hi>hath already committed adultery.</hi> What guard then is ſufficient to ſet vpon theſe ſwift thoughts, which like <hi>lightning,</hi> blaſt and retire; like <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> claps and ſtrikes dead, and all in an inſtant. It is <hi>Gods</hi> goodneſſe to vs, that hath placed in the eye both the Malady, and the Remedy, <hi>Viſum &amp; fletum,</hi> the facultie of ſeeing, and the ſluce of teares, <hi>vt qui delinquant vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dende, poeniteant plorando,</hi> (as one well notes) that they who haue offended by ſeeing, may be recouered by wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Attende auribus.</hi> The Eares are <note place="margin">2. Eares.</note> giuen vs to be <hi>conueyers</hi> of Faith, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18945:14"/> 
               <hi>Conduit pipes</hi> of knowledge; but wee make them impure <hi>tunnells</hi> to ſucke in greedily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the very dregs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ephe 4. 29</note> 
               <hi>and lees of rotten communication,</hi> which <hi>corrupt the manners,</hi> and <hi>defile</hi> the ſoule of man; learne of the deafe Adder to ſtop them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Attende ori, attende linguae,</hi> Take <note place="margin">3. The Tongue. Iam 3. 5 6.</note> heed to thy tongue, <hi>It is a wild beaſt, world of wickedneſſe. It ſets on fire the whole frame of Nature.</hi> It ſpeakes ill of them that are in authority, blurs innocency, ſets priuate men together by the eares, diſturbes the publike peace of the State. The <hi>Portcullis</hi> of the Teeth, and the <hi>Counter-ſcarfe</hi> of the lips, are not ſufficient to keepe in this vnruly member; vnleſſe with <hi>Dauid</hi> we daily pray, <hi>Set a watch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 3</note> 
               <hi>the doores of my lips,</hi> &amp; that God heare vs, which we haue need to doe vnceſſantly. For the mouth though it be <hi>Lyra animata,</hi> a liuing Harpe, yet
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18945:14"/> it is more apt to be a <hi>Babylonian dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimer,</hi> then an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> for the <hi>Songs of Zyon.</hi> I might heere blocke vp the other Ports, and purſue the reſt of the <hi>Traytors:</hi> but let it ſuffice that as in the ſuppreſſion of a great Rebellion, I ſhew the heads of the chiefe Rebels (as it were) vpon ſtakes.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot paſſe by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out looking into the <hi>Traitors vault,</hi> the <hi>Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heart as it is the Center of the <note place="margin">4. The Heart.</note> body, is but a little lumpe of fleſh, and <hi>will ſcarſely ſerue a Kite for a breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt,</hi> yet <hi>all the world will not ſerue it to wander in:</hi> there is ſuch an <hi>endleſſe</hi> maze of exorbitant <hi>deſires</hi> in it: it continually caſteth vp ſulphureous flames of <hi>luſt</hi> and <hi>reuenge.</hi> And which makes the malice and malady thereof more incurable, that of the <hi>heart,</hi> is a ſecret and ſubtile wickedneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18945:15"/> to man, himſelfe, or others. <hi>The heart of the ſonnes of men is full of euill,</hi> and <hi>madneſſe is in their heart</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 93.</note> 
               <hi>while they liue, ſaith the wiſeman. Eccl.</hi> 9. 3. And againe, <hi>Cor hominis Deo, vt lutum figulo,</hi> mans heart is in Gods hands, as clay in the potters. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſaith an ancient <hi>Father,</hi> It is indeede <hi>lutum deo,</hi> as <hi>ſtiffe</hi> and <hi>hard</hi> clay to <hi>God,</hi> had neede of much <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering,</hi> before it can be made <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> will: But it is alſo, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Doemoni,</hi> a heart of fleſh to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, very pliable to any wickedneſſe he ſhall put it to, or into it.</p>
            <p>Should wee neuer ſee ill example, ſhould wee liue out of any outward tentation, yet our owne heart in it ſelfe is ſo wicked, that it would tempt vs to, and teach vs all manner of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; there is ſuch a perpetuall ſpring of wickedneſſe there, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Gods</hi> ſpeciall Grace, we could not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18945:15"/> one minute of our life, ceaſe to doe wickedly in the higheſt degree. <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>reliqui, ſed cor meum non reliqui,</hi> I haue left all, but my heart, I cannot leaue it, (ſaith Saint <hi>Baſil)</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe. In that he had his <hi>heart</hi> with him, he had ill tentations enough. And were it not for this deceitfull, deceiueable heart of ours, other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward tentations could not hurt vs. <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> were not effectually tempted, vntill they were corrupted in their hearts. Let euery man then apply to his heart that which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeakes to <hi>Hieruſalem, O Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>waſh thine heart from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued: how long ſhall thy vaine thoughts lodge within thee.</hi> It were well our wicked thoughts would <hi>lodge</hi> and <hi>abide</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs; but they breake out into wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deeds. So our Sauiour tells vs, that <hi>euery thing that defiles the man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 18</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18945:16"/> 
               <hi>cometh from out the heart.</hi> The filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans heart was ſo great, that it was faine to be waſhed with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of waters. And it is growne ſo <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> filthy againe, that all the <hi>water</hi> in the world will not ſerue <hi>to waſh it,</hi> it muſt rather haue a world of <hi>fire</hi> to <hi>purge</hi> it, to conſume it. Euery man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>muſt circumcize his heart. Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 4.</note> will not ſerue the turne, we muſt vſe <hi>Inciſion,</hi> that's not enough: we muſt (as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes) not onely <hi>circumcidere, pare</hi> it about; and <hi>inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, cut it deepe;</hi> but <hi>decidere,</hi> and <hi>excidere,</hi> and <hi>deprimere, cut it off;</hi> and if it riſe againe (like <hi>hidras</hi> heades) cut it <hi>out,</hi> or <hi>preſſe</hi> it <hi>downe,</hi> euen <hi>beate</hi> it to <hi>powder,</hi> and annihilate it, that <hi>God</hi> may <hi>create a new heart</hi> within vs.</p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>Lent-time,</hi> a Time of <hi>faſting,</hi> and <hi>prayer;</hi> a time of <hi>pennance</hi> and <hi>contrition. Lent</hi> in the ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> language ſignifies <hi>the Spring:</hi> now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18945:16"/> then moſt fitly, when our <hi>ranke bloud</hi> recouers the pride of it's ſpring, ſhould we by a <hi>ſlender dyet beat down</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> 
               <hi>our bodies, and keepe them vnder.</hi> Now is the time to put <hi>our kniues to our throat,</hi> to vſe <hi>Daniels fare,</hi> and <hi>Daniels prayer.</hi> By <hi>prayer</hi> will the ſoule learne to command the body, and by <hi>faſting,</hi> the body will learne to <hi>obey</hi> the ſoule. <hi>Nature</hi> is content with a little, <hi>Grace</hi> with leſſe. It is now a time of <hi>mortification,</hi> &amp; aſhes. High-fed <hi>luſt,</hi> and high-wrought <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and high-flowne <hi>pride,</hi> are <hi>Lordly</hi> companions, but are not to be <hi>truſted</hi> with the <hi>Empire;</hi> which if you tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre from <hi>Reaſon</hi> to <hi>Paſsion,</hi> (as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> remoued from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople)</hi> it is the onely way to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine both ſoule and body, as he ruined that which hee thought to enlarge. Such a ſtate of body <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique,</hi> is like the Serpent <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phiſbaena,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18945:17"/> whoſe taile goes formoſt. Wake not therefore to <hi>dreame</hi> of Kingdomes, as the mad <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lacquey did, who tooke himſelfe to be <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> to be but his <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of nothing but his <hi>Indies,</hi> and of the returne of his <hi>Plate-fleets,</hi> and would goe no leſſe then the <hi>vniuerſall</hi> Monarch.</p>
            <p>This is <hi>Spaniſh</hi> pride, beware of it, and vſe towring thoughts, as men vſe riſing Bees, <hi>Caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt vpon them,</hi> let meditation of mortality bring them downe againe. Art thou <hi>rich?</hi> thou art but rich earth, and <hi>Gold Ore</hi> is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher then thou. Art thou <hi>honoured,</hi> and euen <hi>adored</hi> of thy enemie? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>rotten blocke</hi> hath been made a greater <hi>Idoll.</hi> Art thou <hi>beautifull?</hi> thy <hi>picture</hi> well drawne will one day be better to <hi>locke</hi> on, then the <hi>face</hi> it was drawne by. Remember thou art <hi>rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mortall, honourably mortall, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18945:17"/> 
               <hi>mortall,</hi> how euer mortall. Look oncc into a <hi>charnell</hi> houſe, a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and ſee if by the bones, or the skuls, thou canſt diſcouer who was <hi>rich, beautifull,</hi> or <hi>honourable:</hi> where now are the <hi>Nimrods,</hi> and <hi>Belſhazzers,</hi> the <hi>Gyants</hi> of the old world? their names we finde regiſtred, but 'tis for their Gyantly vices; and they are now <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter potentes, qui potenter peccauerunt, &amp; potenter torquebuntur,</hi> amongſt the mighty men, which ſhall be mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tormented.</p>
            <p>This is a time to manacle the <hi>hands,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 6. 7.</note> thoſe inſtruments of <hi>violence, bribery</hi> and <hi>extortion:</hi> to gird vp the <hi>loynes,</hi> thoſe Seminaries and bankes of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence:</hi> to ſtocke the <hi>feet,</hi> thoſe ſwift ſupplanting blood-drawing <hi>Curſitors,</hi> and in a word, to <hi>crucify the olde man.</hi> Let not the <hi>proclamation</hi> and the <hi>Almanache</hi> be the only argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and proofes that 'ts <hi>Lent:</hi> let
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18945:18"/> our brawnie <hi>knees,</hi> our courſe <hi>backes,</hi> our thin <hi>bellies,</hi> our amended <hi>liues,</hi> proclaime the ſame; and ſo ſtop the complaint of <hi>Saluian, Chriſtianè vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere dedecus eſt,</hi> to liue like good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to faſt and pray, is turn'd to our reproach. 'Tis ſigne the <hi>old</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent doth lurke in our <hi>old</hi> wals, when being <hi>ſicke of the Mother,</hi> we ſtill long after <hi>forbidden</hi> fruit. Let it be thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion to giue each part his due, to thy <hi>ſoule</hi> the gouernment; to thy <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> neceſſaries, <hi>raiment</hi> and <hi>food, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe</hi> withall, and <hi>correction.</hi> And in this there muſt be obſerued a <hi>Ne quid nimis,</hi> a due proportion to either. The ſoule ought to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>rule,</hi> but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tyrannize</hi> ouer the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The Primitiue and purer diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline doth not put iron whips and lanching kniues into your hands to cut and furrow your fleſh. Let the Prieſts of Romiſh <hi>Baal</hi> vſe and inioyn
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18945:18"/> ſuch exerciſe and <hi>heatheniſh</hi> inciſion. I commend vnto you a <hi>weeding hook</hi> and a <hi>pruning knife,</hi> to pare away lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurie and exceſſe, and to pull vp <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the root of bitterneſſe. <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 15</note> 
               <hi>modo imperet,</hi> let my Son kill me ſo he may be Emperour (ſaith <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina</hi> of <hi>Nero.)</hi> It were a happy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would our proud <hi>fleſh</hi> be content to ſay, Let me be <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,</hi> ſo my ſoule may <hi>raigne</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> S. <hi>Lucy</hi> in the <hi>Legend,</hi> who pul'd out her own eyes, miſtooke the Text. A <hi>darling ſinne</hi> is that <hi>rigbt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 39</note> 
               <hi>eye,</hi> which thou art to <hi>pull out;</hi> and ſome <hi>wicked beloued</hi> inſtrument is that <hi>right hand,</hi> which we are to <hi>cut off.</hi> If we cocker <hi>Adoniah,</hi> our owne fleſh, let vs know that one day this <note place="margin">1 Kings 1. 5, 6.</note> wanton will proue a <hi>Rebell,</hi> and wee ſhall be ſcourged with a <hi>Scorpion</hi> of our owne <hi>bowels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time we ſee that this <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18945:19"/> 
               <hi>tibi,</hi> is a <hi>frontlet</hi> for our eyes, a <hi>iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> for our eares, a golden <hi>chaine</hi> for our necks, a <hi>bracelet</hi> for our armes, a <hi>tablet</hi> for our breſts, and a <hi>priuy coat</hi> for the whole man.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon occaſion of the <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 6.</note> words of the <hi>Spouſe, Set me as a ſeale vpon thy heart, and as a ſignet vpon thy arme,</hi> doth ſweetly obſerue, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>ſeale</hi> on our <hi>forehead,</hi> when we openly confeſſe him; a ſeale vpon our <hi>heart,</hi> when wee ſincerely loue him; a <hi>ſignet</hi> vpon our <hi>arme,</hi> when wee worke righteouſneſſe and fence our ſelues againſt theſe <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> and <hi>Edomites,</hi> our ſoules enemies. Thus haue we paſſed the firſt watch, <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende corpori, Take heed to thy body.</hi> We enter now vpon the ſecond, <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende animae,</hi> which is <hi>Cuſtodia Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij,</hi> the watch about the Palace, or the Kings Pauilion. <hi>Si tanti Vitrum, quanti Margarita?</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If flaring Glaſſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18945:19"/> be ſo valued, at what ſhall the orient Pearle be priſed? If we be ſo carefull for the <hi>Cabinet,</hi> the body, how many millions of new and greater cares ſhould we take for the <hi>Iewell,</hi> which is our ſoule?</p>
            <p>Prouide a good guard for this <hi>Queene,</hi> ſhe is the great <hi>Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the <hi>ſpouſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It was no baſe purchaſe, which coſt the <hi>Sonne of God</hi> his deareſt heart-bloud. <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 19</note> It is no meane booty which Sathan ſo hotly purſues by <hi>compaſsing Sea</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and land.</hi> It is not <hi>a thouſand rammes, nor ten thouſand riuers of oyle, nor ſo many ſacrificed ſonnes the fruit of thy body, can ſatisfie for the ſinnes of thy ſoule. It coſt more to redeeme a ſoule.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mica. 6. 7.</note> How much more? <hi>Dauid</hi> wants <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetique</hi> to expreſſe it, and where he failes, who can tel the proportion, or rather infinite diſproportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt any price, and that great pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſſe.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18945:20"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> who beſt knew the price of ſoules (as being ſole purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer) doth paſſe all the world in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew of the ranſome of our ſoules: <hi>what ſhall a man giue in recompenſe of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 8. 37.</note> 
               <hi>his ſoule?</hi> and in the verſe before, <hi>wbat ſhall it profit a man, though he win the whole world, if he looſe his ſoule?</hi> Sure he will be a moſt wretched bankrupt by the bargaine. In the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> Scale, <hi>Anima muſcae eſt ſole praeſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tior,</hi> The ſoule of a ſilly <hi>flye</hi> is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent (in nature though not in vſe) then the glorious <hi>Sunne</hi> in the firmament. In the <hi>Ciuilians</hi> account, <hi>Omne mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum eſt ineſtimabile,</hi> Euery limbe of a man is vnvalewable: Can you giue me the iuſt price of a <hi>leg,</hi> of an <hi>arme,</hi> of an <hi>eye?</hi> Now Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> hath <note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt.</note> well obſerued, <hi>God</hi> hath giuen <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra duplicia,</hi> two eyes, two armes, two legs, that the failing of the one, may be ſupplied by the other. <hi>Animam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18945:20"/> 
               <hi>vnam,</hi> but one ſoule, when that is loſt, ther's no ſupply. Admit there were ſo many worlds, as there are motes in the ſunne: lay them all in one ſcale, they will not counteruaile one ſoule, which <hi>is not redeemed with Siluer and Gold, but with the precious bloud of Chriſt, as of a lamb vndefiled.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 19</note> Oh the prodigals of our age! I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to poynt at their vnthriftineſſe: what coſt and care is beſtowed vpon <hi>houſes, horſes, haukes, dogs?</hi> meane while what cheape account, what wilfull neglect of ſoules? The <hi>houſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch.</hi> liues.</note> muſt be like that of <hi>Valerius</hi> magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently built, and furniſhed, the <hi>horſe</hi> fat &amp; faire, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>all things muſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>be braue, and gorgeous;</hi> but there is no care taken, that there be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>beautifull ſoule.</hi> Should I tell this preſſe of people, that that there were many <hi>cutpurſes</hi> amongſt them (as there vſe to be in crowdes) euery man
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18945:21"/> would preſently put his hand into his pocket, and looke to his purſe. The ſafeſt man here is in ſuch danger, as he had neede of ſome friends to cry <hi>loud</hi> and <hi>ſuddenly, Take heede to thy ſelfe.</hi> Giue me leaue to tell you, yee haue brought with you, euen within your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues an <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> a <hi>heart-ſtealer,</hi> euen now whilſt I call vpon you to the <hi>ſcruteny of conſcience,</hi> to arraigne your ſelues <hi>in interiore domo,</hi> in the inner cloſet (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> cals it.) There is an <hi>Abſolon</hi> at the gates, that <note place="margin">S. Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>ſtealeth away the hearts of the people. Looke to your ſelues,</hi> and apprehende <note place="margin">1 King. 15. 6.</note> the traitour, your <hi>ſelfe-loue,</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-flatterie. Deliuer me, O Lord, from the euill man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> id eſt,</hi> from my <hi>ſelfe,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that holy Father S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <note place="margin">S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </note> one lay his hand vpon his heart, and ſay to himſelfe in the language of the prophet <hi>Abacuck, I will ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Abac. 2. 1.</note> 
               <hi>my watch.</hi> I for my part will looke
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18945:21"/> to one, <hi>I'le take heede to my ſoule.</hi> There are two ſorts of euil thoughts, 1. <hi>immiſsae</hi> or <hi>iniectae,</hi> infuſed or caſt into vs, which are of the Deuils dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into the heart. 2. <hi>aſcèndentes,</hi> which as vapours naturally ariſe out of the heart. A 3. ſort there are good, <hi>deſcendentes, inſpired</hi> by the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> clap a <hi>guard</hi> of <hi>thoughts</hi> vpon your <hi>thoughts,</hi> of <hi>good</hi> ones vpon <hi>bad</hi> ones; <hi>preuent</hi> them, by diuine medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, <hi>diuert</hi> them, by feruent eia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations; <hi>correct</hi> them, by ſighs, and ſpeedy repentance. In bad thoughts ye may obſerue, <hi>ingreſſum et progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> the ingreſſe and the progreſſe. For the firſt; the vapor will aſcend you cannot hinder it; t'is well if you can but come to this to quench, and to repreſſe it, that it goe no further: and when your ſtrength failes, pray with Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> in <hi>Euſebius, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, cupio ſaluari, ſed non permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18945:22"/> 
               <hi>cogitationes meae, has reprime, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Anthon. in Euſeb.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſu &amp; ſalua me,</hi> Lord, I would gladly be ſaued, but my thoughts will not permit me: ſweet Ieſu repreſſe theſe, and ſaue me. And for the other, Take along with you Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> councell and comfort, <hi>Si tentationes pulſant cor tuum, ſuſpira.</hi> If tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions beat at thy heart, ſigh and eaſe it. <hi>Si non ſuperant, reſpira,</hi> but if they ouercome thee not, take heart agrace again, take breath &amp; be comforted: if <hi>they</hi> haue not ouercome <hi>thee, thou</hi> haſt overcome them. Marke how the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> in this <hi>guard</hi> of the ſoule, doth excite a watchman to grapple with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſinne, and is a <hi>monitor</hi> to checke euery ill motion. <hi>Idolatry is couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and couetouſneſſe is Idolatry. Attende vtri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> Is there feare of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry by mixture of nations? <hi>Attende tibi ipſi.</hi> Take heede of <hi>Canaanites.</hi> It is the ſcope of the text, and the text
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18945:22"/> is a ſpeciall <hi>Amulet</hi> againſt that infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious ſinne. <hi>Peccare dicitur quaſi pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licare,</hi> ſinne intices like an harlot. Such ſinners eſpecially <hi>goe a whoring after their owne inuentions,</hi> the ſoule that thus ſinneth is an adultreſſe, a <hi>Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,</hi> proſtitutes her ſelfe to the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or creatures. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the pyed Oxe <hi>Apis,</hi> and thence <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 4</note> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did learne to make a <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calfe.</hi> The <hi>Canaanites</hi> adore the Moone; ther's danger that the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits may offer <hi>Cakes to the Queene of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 7. 18.</note> 
               <hi>heauen.</hi> Of all outlandiſh and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhions, new-faſhions in <hi>Religion</hi> are moſt dangerous, the ſubuerſion of the State. Doth <hi>Couetouſneſſe</hi> make a drudge of the body, and a ſlaue of the ſoule? <hi>Attende tibi, non tuis,</hi> looke to ſelfe, not to pelfe. Set not a higher rate vpon a <hi>wife,</hi> a <hi>farme,</hi> a <hi>preferment,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 14.</note> then vpon thy ſoule: prize not things <hi>temporall,</hi> as if they were <hi>eternall;</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18945:23"/> not things <hi>eternall,</hi> as if they were <hi>temporall.</hi> Saint <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> doth fitly <note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt.</note> compare toyling worldlings to men that worke in a dangerous myne, <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fodiunt &amp; necantur,</hi> in ſeeking gold they dig their owne graues, and are buryed aliue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Doth <hi>Curioſity</hi> peep in at a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours window, and meddle without commiſſion? <hi>Attende tibi, non alijs, non alienis,</hi> looke to thy ſelfe, not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men or matters, thou haſt worke enough at home, <hi>Occupa te in proprijs vitijs, Pull out the beame that's in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 6. 42.</note> 
               <hi>thine own eye firſt.</hi> [Firſt ſweepe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine owne doore, before thou beateſt thy neighbor with the <hi>broom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke.</hi> Be thine owne examiner one halfe of the day, and then wilt thou haue little leiſure (I ſuppoſe) the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther halfe to ſit as Iudge vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.] Rigid cenſurers, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, who <hi>cry out</hi> of ſinnes in others,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18945:23"/> and <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with their owne, are like cunning <hi>Robbers,</hi> who firſt raiſe the <hi>Hue and Cry,</hi> that whiles they purſue others as ſeeming honeſt <hi>Officers,</hi> themſelues may eſcape who were the offenders.</p>
            <p>Doth <hi>Security,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that poyſon in a golden cup,</hi> caſt vs into a deepe ſleepe. <hi>Attende tibi ipſi,</hi> Friends cry, and fall; Foes come on. <hi>Simon dormis, &amp; Iudas non dormit?</hi> Doth <hi>Peter</hi> ſleepe, when <hi>Iudas</hi> wakes? The Deuill like <hi>Dalilah,</hi> will not ſuffer a man to ſee his danger till it be too late. <hi>Vp Sampſon, the Philiſtims are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 12.</note> 
               <hi>vpon thee.</hi> And if <hi>Sampſon</hi> will not vſe his eyes in time, hee ſhall looſe them. What is a <hi>State</hi> without vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy, but a <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> a vaſt body without eyes, running headlong to it own ruine? And an eye to our ſelues will not make all ſure without an eye to <hi>Heauen.</hi> Thither our ſoule (which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18945:24"/> came thence, and thither will) will teach vs to looke. <hi>Sibi maximè atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act 17. 28.</note> 
               <hi>qui maximè attendit Deo,</hi> Hee beſt lookes to himſelfe, that beſt looks towards God. <hi>In him we liue, we moue, and haue our being</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with him and by him, and through him we are,</hi> and can doe all things; without him we not onely <hi>can</hi> doe nothing, but <hi>are</hi> nothing. And thus am I come to the third watch which is the laſt, <hi>Cuſtodia Templi,</hi> the watch about the temple.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> vpon the fourth of <hi>Ezech.</hi> doth well note, that <hi>Cuſtodes Templi,</hi> the warders of the myſticall Temple do betoken the deuout ſoules that <hi>frequent</hi> the church, and by a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kinde of of violence, <hi>keepe poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> houſe. In humane Policy <hi>Feare</hi> is but a bad and vnſafe keeper, not like long to hold out; a <hi>iaylor</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a <hi>guardian:</hi> but in chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity the <hi>Feare of God is the beſt dore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18945:24"/> 
               <hi>of the Temple.</hi> And <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nazian.</note> in the praiſe of <hi>Hieron,</hi> doth praiſe Piety <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>the greateſt and ſafeſt guard of mans life.</hi> The <hi>greateſt</hi> haue greateſt need of this guard; and the <hi>pooreſt</hi> are not ſo poore, but they may be thus guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all perils. For euery good ſoule hath a <hi>train'd band</hi> of faculties, euer ready <hi>ſummon'd</hi> to waite vpon <hi>God.</hi> And to ſuch as wait on him, <hi>God</hi> will ſend <hi>aid from Heauen.</hi> In vaine doth <hi>Ioſhua</hi> lift vp his hand to fight againſt <hi>Amalech,</hi> except <hi>Moſes</hi> lift vp his hands to pray for <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> when wee haue done all wee can to keepe our <note place="margin">Exo. 17. 13</note> ſelues, we muſt fly for protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the great <hi>keeper</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who <hi>neuer ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> nor <hi>ſlumbreth,</hi> or els we haue loſt, <note place="margin">Pſal. 121. 4</note> &amp; ſhall looſe our labour &amp; our ſelues. Our beſt Armory is in the <hi>Temple,</hi> &amp; not in the <hi>Tower.</hi> Waite vpon God, and he will appoint a guard of <hi>Angels</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 11</note>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18945:25"/> 
               <hi>to wait vpon thee;</hi> yea God doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully order his thoughts towards men, when men doe leaſt order their thoghts towards God. <hi>God</hi> doth <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 6.</note> the meanes for our ſafety, when we do not know the <hi>liſts,</hi> and order of the <hi>troops</hi> that guard vs: <hi>Lord, what is man that thou art mindfull of him, or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8 4.</note> 
               <hi>the ſonne of man that thou ſo regardeſt him?</hi> yea Lord, what is man that he is ſo vnmindfull of thee: or the ſonne of man, that he ſo little regards thee? And yet from on high thou regardeſt the loweſt, euen the <hi>refuſe,</hi> the <hi>off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skowring</hi> and rubbiſh of men. A word of comfort to the leaſt &amp; loweſt here. What though the vnpreferd, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided for <hi>Courtier</hi> be compared to a <hi>Blackamore, In ortu ſolis poſitus, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet colorem noctis,</hi> He liues where the Sunne riſeth euery day in his eies, and yet his face looks like night. Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate man who euer thou be, if thou
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18945:25"/> waiteſt vpon <hi>God,</hi> know that <hi>his eyes are vpon thee for good,</hi> and that a <hi>roab</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8</note> and a <hi>crowne</hi> is laid vp for thee. Thou haſt not here <hi>glittering ſeruants</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thee; yet haſt thou the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moone</hi> to run before thee with their glorious torches, both day and night. Yea, <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>giuen his Angels charge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 91. 11 Heb. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>concerning thee.</hi> They are miniſtring ſpirits ſent forth for thy ſake, thou art an hopefull <hi>heire</hi> of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Some hurrying <hi>Iehu,</hi> may demand, what need haue wee to looke euery man to himſelfe? If <hi>God</hi> doe muſter his <hi>Angels</hi> to looke to euery one of vs? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">So. </seg>
               </label> Know that the <hi>prime cauſe</hi> doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther include, than exclude <hi>ſubordinate</hi> meanes. <hi>God</hi> can, but doth not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily worke without them. He hath made <hi>Starres</hi> to direct the <hi>Pylot,</hi> but he made not Starres to <hi>ſteere</hi> the ſhip. <hi>O culus ad Coelum, manus ad clauum,</hi> there muſt be an eye to Heauen, and a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18945:26"/> hand to the Helme: when we worke with <hi>God, God</hi> will worke for vs. Did the <hi>Eaſterne wiſe-men</hi> neglect the vſe <note place="margin">Matth. 2. 2.</note> of tongues, and feet, becauſe they had a Starre to guide them? A glorious band of Angels ſhall be your <hi>conuoy</hi> in all your waies, <hi>In vijs, non in praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs,</hi> in your waies chalked out by the line of the law, and the rule of the Word, not in your headlong courſes, and deſperate downfalls. And that you may know your way, <hi>Attende Legi,</hi> looke to the Law, how readeſt thou? there's the old way the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Looke in <hi>Malachy,</hi> there you are bid to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber it, vpon the going <note place="margin">Malac. 4. 4</note> out of it in the laſt of the Prophets, &amp; to <hi>Chriſt</hi> (prefigured in <hi>Eliah)</hi> the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filler of the law, who is the new way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Attende verbo,</hi> look to Gods word, there's the <hi>pillar of fire</hi> that goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all true. <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the way. The way of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> hath many beaten
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18945:26"/> pathes: Keepe theſe with thy heart, and they well kept, will keepe thy <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 4.</note> heart, ſo that it ſhall liue for euer.</p>
            <p>The Heart is an <hi>vnskilfull</hi> &amp; <hi>guile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> guide, it had need to be guided, and kept, <hi>Keepe thy heart with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 23</note> 
               <hi>for out of it are the iſſues of life.</hi> Therefore follow not the wayes of thine owne heart, in which there be ſo many windings, and turnings, that <hi>Anſelme</hi> compares it to a <hi>Mill</hi> that's euer <hi>grinding,</hi> ſtill ſetting vs on worke with more commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, then euer <hi>God</hi> gaue vs. He gaue vs but one in the Law, <hi>Fac &amp; viues,</hi> doe this and liue. One in the Goſpell, <hi>Crede &amp; viues,</hi> beleeue and thou ſhalt liue: or rather one in both, <hi>Ama &amp; viues,</hi> loue and liue. If thou followeſt the many <hi>by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</hi> thereof, thou goeſt <hi>in infinitum;</hi> and there is <hi>Error immenſus,</hi> an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wandring, and the end of that error is <hi>horror</hi> and endleſſe <hi>confuſion.</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18945:27"/> But giue thou thy heart vnto <hi>God</hi> the preſeruer of ſoules. <hi>Commit thy waies</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 5.</note> 
               <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> who is both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>true way, and a true guide,</hi> for he is the truth, <hi>Et ipſe eſt via, ipſe eſt patria,</hi> he <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 6.</note> is thy way, he is thy dwelling Citie. If thou walkeſt in this way, which is but one, in this truth, which is but one, there's <hi>aliquis terminꝰ,</hi> ſome end; thou art ſure to come at laſt to thy wayes end, <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Peace:</hi> he is the God of both, he will bring thee home to himſelfe, and as he ſaid to <hi>Abraham Ipſe erit tibi merces magna nimis,</hi> hee <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 1.</note> will be thy exceeding great reward.</p>
            <p>Meane while, in this our preſent warfare, though his pleaſure be not, that we ſhould fight at our owne coſt and charge, yet his charge here is, <hi>vt quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> attendat ſibi ipſi,</hi> that euery man ſhould <hi>ſtand vpon his own guard,</hi> ſerue in his owne <hi>perſon,</hi> and his own <hi>furniture. Atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de tibi ipſi,</hi> I haue heard
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18945:27"/> of an abuſe in Country <hi>Muſters,</hi> that diuers ſhew borrowed Armes: looke into their houſes, ye ſhall finde them naked, and vnprouided for the enemy. I would to God, the caſe were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in our ſpirituall <hi>armour.</hi> Many in good dayes can diſcourſe of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith, <hi>Iobs</hi> patience, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> care to preſerue his ſoule; and in ſo doing, they do but ſhew other mens armour. For when they are preſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and put to the ſtreſſe in the day of tentation, when it is their turne to watch, they giue no euidence of their own <hi>care, faith,</hi> or <hi>patience.</hi> No bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing, no ſubſtitution will ſerue the turne here, <hi>Attende tibi ipſi,</hi> looke to thy ſelfe, thou canſt not looke to thy ſelfe by a <hi>Proxie,</hi> or <hi>Deputie.</hi> The good Kings <hi>Dauid, Aſah,</hi> and <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> did not ſerue God by their <hi>Chapleines,</hi> in the dayes of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, their owne prayers are for euer
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18945:28"/> Chronicled. And it is a high point of Piety worthy to be chronicled, that our <hi>Moſes, Summus loco, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus exemplo,</hi> our good King, who is firſt in place, hath alſo been formoſt in example, is the <hi>Coryphaeus,</hi> the firſt <hi>proclaimer,</hi> and in his own <hi>perſon kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of ſolemne Faſts,</hi> moſt <hi>frequent</hi> at prayers, a royall <hi>praecentor</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> houſe and ſeruice. Then doe men on earth liue like thoſe glorious <hi>Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> (Angels) in Heauen, when they moſt diligently waite vpon <hi>God.</hi> It ſhould be amongſt men, as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Elements,</hi> the <hi>higher</hi> the <hi>purer,</hi> the <hi>neerer</hi> to the Starres, the more <hi>conformable</hi> to heauenly moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yea the great <hi>Rulers among the Starres</hi> (whom God made to gouern <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 16.</note> day and night) do giue this light and example to great <hi>Rulers amongst men,</hi> that they ſhould euer be watchfull, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in motion, for the good of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18945:28"/> and regulated by the <hi>prime Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> ſo doing, theſe great lights ſhall neuer be eclipſed. Thinke not that <hi>Stellae nebuloſae,</hi> the leſſer ſtarres onely <hi>borrow</hi> light, but remember the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſtarres receiue the <hi>greater</hi> light: And if there be not a faire <hi>aſpect from,</hi> and <hi>to</hi> the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> they ſuffer the greater <hi>eclipſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop &amp; ouerſeer,</hi> out of his high watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tower, whence he beholdeth all our wayes. It is therefore meet, that we in all our wayes ſhould ſet him before our eyes: he giueth (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>life and breath vnto all.</hi> To the <hi>Ant</hi> as well as to the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</hi> If we liue in <hi>God,</hi> rather than in <hi>our ſelues,</hi> we muſt endeuour to liue rather <hi>to God</hi> than <hi>to our ſelues.</hi> If <hi>God</hi> doe beſtow breath vpon vs, oh let vs beſtow the beſt of our breath vpon <hi>God. Attende deo,</hi> waite vpon <hi>God,</hi> that hath made thee the <hi>maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18945:29"/> of Nature; and redeemed thee' the <hi>prime obiect</hi> of Grace, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thee, to be an <hi>heire of Glory.</hi> Oh <note place="margin">Luke 1. 37.</note> let thy ſoule be a deuout <hi>Anna,</hi> diuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the world, and wedded to the Temple; yea let thy zealous ſoule ſpeake of this <hi>mantle</hi> of fleſh, and mount vp in a <hi>fiery chariot:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">2 Kigs 2. 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Oh my ſoule looke vpward, be not glued to this baſe earth;</hi> grouell not in this <hi>Cabul,</hi> a land of durt, in <hi>Hyrams</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kigs 7. 13.</note> map; ſtoope not to <hi>euery,</hi> to <hi>any</hi> baſe Lure. The proper motion of the ſoule is an <hi>aſcenſion vnto God;</hi> not by the <hi>phyloſophers</hi> ſcale: for Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> confeſſeth, that this ladder <hi>per exteriora,</hi> by outward meanes, is too ſhort to reach to heauen, there muſt be a <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder to reach home.</p>
            <p>The <hi>pile</hi> of creatures is but the <hi>Mount</hi> vnder our feet. The <hi>illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> vnderſtanding and the <hi>ſanctified</hi> will, are the two <hi>Seraphicall</hi> wings
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18945:29"/> that carry vs vp before the throne of Grace.</p>
            <p>The life of the deuoute man is a kinde of a continuall extaſie, their ſoules doe wait vpon <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries</hi> of heauen, euen while their mortified bodies doe walke towards their graues; and like drowzy watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ready to drop into this ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie gutter. I haue kept you too long waiting vpon this watch: to draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>diſcharging</hi> therof for this time. Dearely beloued in our <hi>Lord,</hi> ctc. Be we excited euery one of vs, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to <hi>keepe</hi> this watch, that we may walke on in the power of <hi>God,</hi> and the ſtrength of our prayers. It is not a <hi>moate</hi> of the Sea, or a <hi>wall</hi> of Cliffs, nor our owne armes that can defend vs, except <hi>God</hi> fight for vs; except our Land bee compaſſed with the <hi>Ocean</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> mercies, and <hi>forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> by the <hi>rock Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Be firſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18945:30"/> at peace at home within your ſelues. Loue brotherly loue, which <hi>is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>bond of peace;</hi> then looke to your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred</hi> foes, your boſome traytors, your enemies at <hi>home;</hi> and ye ſhall be the ſafer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your enemies <hi>abroad.</hi> It doth coſt other nations much effuſion of their owne bloud and others, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them ſelues and keepe back their enemies; ſhall we ſit at home, with our thumbs vnder our girdles <hi>(coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly,)</hi> with our naked throats <hi>(cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly)</hi> expecting the ſword of our enemies? [chooſe rather to <hi>looſe</hi> our liues, than <hi>lend our monyes</hi> to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of our <hi>good King,</hi> and the <hi>defence</hi> of his &amp; our <hi>three Kingdomes?]</hi> At leaſt ſhall we not ſpend our <hi>breath,</hi> or rather the <hi>groanes</hi> of the ſpirit, in our owne defence, in the defence of our wiues and children, lands and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, againſt ſo proud and cruell an enemie?</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:18945:30"/>
            <p> Oh peirce the heauens with your <hi>vollies</hi> of prayers, for the <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>ſtate,</hi> your owne <hi>welfare,</hi> and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of your ſoules, that our <hi>Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> (this Iland) may ſtill be <hi>Gremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pacis,</hi> the lap and boſome <hi>of peace,</hi> euen to ſtrangers; and that our ſelues, euen euery one of vs, may enioy the peace of our owne boſomes. We are incompaſſed with whole ſeas of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; it will be our onely wiſdome and ſafety, to <hi>anchor</hi> our ſelues vpon God, to ſaile by the compaſſe of his word; and to haue an eye to that <hi>Pharos,</hi> that guides vs to the <hi>land of promiſe,</hi> to the land of the liuing; ſo ſhall that of <hi>Tertullian</hi> be verified, <hi>Sperando timebimus, timendo cauebimus, cauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſalui erimus,</hi> In hoping wee ſhall feare, in fearing, take heede, and by taking heede, be ſaued. If wee keepe our bodies as the <hi>temples</hi> of God, and <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 1.</note> our ſoules as his <hi>pauilion;</hi> he wil make
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18945:31"/> his owne name our <hi>tower of defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>diſcharge</hi> of my conſcience and duty at this time; but yet I may not quite <hi>diſcharge,</hi> and breake vp this <hi>watch;</hi> we muſt at all times ſtand vpon this watch, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lay downe our <hi>armour,</hi> till wee ſhall lay downe our liues, and be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated to that kingdome, where there is no enemy, nor danger.</p>
            <p>To the which he bring vs, who hath ſo dearly bought vs, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> by the conduct of his holy ſpirit. To whom with the Father &amp;c. three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, one true, euer liuing God, wee deſire to aſcribe, as his due, and our duty, all praiſe, power, honour, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and thankſgiuing, this day and euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18945:31"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18945:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
